I was recently traveling in the Highlands of New Guinea,
في الآونة الأخيرة، كنت مسافرة في مرتفعات غينيا الجديدة،
and I was talking with a man who had three wives.
وكنت أتحدث إلى رجل متزوج من ثلاث نساء.
I asked him, "How many wives would you like to have?"
سألته:"كم زوجة تريد؟"
And there was this long pause,
وأطبق صمت طويل،
and I thought to myself,
فكرت في سري،
"Is he going to say five?
"هل سيقول خمسة؟
Is he going to say 10?
هل سيقول عشرة؟
Is he going to say 25?"
هل سيقول خمسة وعشرون؟"
And he leaned towards me
انحنى نحوي
and he whispered, "None."
وهمس قائلاً:"ولا واحدة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Eighty-six percent of human societies permit a man to have several wives:
86% من المجتمعات الإنسانية ، تسمح للرجل بتعدد الزوجات:
polygyny.
تعدد الجينات.
But in the vast majority of these cultures,
ولكن في الغالبية العظمة لهذه الثقافات،
only about five or ten percent of men actually do have several wives.
حوالي فقط 5%أو 10% لديهم أكثر من زوجة.
Having several partners can be a toothache.
أن يكون لك أكثر من شريك أشبه بألم الأسنان.
In fact, co-wives can fight with each other,
في الحقيقة ، باستطاعة الزوجات أن يتقاتلوا مع بعضهم البعض،
sometimes they can even poison each other's children.
وفي بعض الأحيان ،يُسمموا أطفال بعض.
And you've got to have a lot of cows, a lot of goats,
ويجب أن تملك الكثير من الأبقار الكثير من الماعز،
a lot of money, a lot of land,
الكثير من المال، والكثير من الأراضي،
in order to build a harem.
من أجل أن تبني الحرملك.
We are a pair-bonding species.
نحن من الأنواع التي ترتبط كأزواج.
Ninety-seven percent of mammals do not pair up to rear their young;
97% من الثديات لا ترتبط إلا في أواخر الشباب:
human beings do.
كذلك يفعل البشر.
I'm not suggesting that we're not --
أنا لا أقترح بأننا--
that we're necessarily sexually faithful to our partners.
بأننا بالضرورة مرتبطين بشركائنا جنسياً.
I've looked at adultery in 42 cultures,
لقد اتطلعت على الزنا في 42 حضارة،
I understand, actually, some of the genetics of it,
في الواقع ، أفهم بعض من علم الوراثة فيه
and some of the brain circuitry of it.
وبعض دارات الدماغ فيه.
It's very common around the world,
إنه أمر شائع جداً في جميع أنحاء العالم
but we are built to love.
ولكن خلقنا لنحب.
How is technology changing love?
كيف التكنولوجيا تغير الحب؟
I'm going to say almost not at all.
وأنا سأقول لا على الإطلاق.
I study the brain.
أنا أدرس الدماغ.
I and my colleagues have put over 100 people into a brain scanner --
أنا وزملائي وضعنا أكثر من مئة شخص في ماسح الدماغ
people who had just fallen happily in love,
أُناس سعداء وقعوا حديثا بالحب
people who had just been rejected in love
وأناس واجهوا الرفض بالحب
and people who are in love long-term.
وأُناس في الحب منذ مدة كبيرة.
And it is possible to remain "in love" long-term.
وإنه من المحتمل البقاء بالحب لفترة كبيرة.
And I've long ago maintained
ولقد حافظت بعد فترة طويلة
that we've evolved three distinctly different brain systems
بعد أن قمنا بتطوير ثلاث أنظمة دماغ مختلفة بشكل واضح
for mating and reproduction:
للتزاوج والتكاثر:
sex drive,
الدافع الجنسي،
feelings of intense romantic love
مشاعر الحب الرومانسي الشديد
and feelings of deep cosmic attachment to a long-term partner.
ومشاعر التعلق لأبعد الحدود مع شريك على المدى الطويل.
And together, these three brain systems --
ومع بعض ، هذه الأنظمة الثلاث--
with many other parts of the brain --
مع أجزاء عديدة من الدماغ--
orchestrate our sexual, our romantic and our family lives.
تنظم حياتنا الجنسية و الرومانسية وحياتنا العائلية.
But they lie way below the cortex,
لكن تقع تحت القشرة
way below the limbic system where we feel our emotions,
تحت الجهاز الحوفي، حيث نشعر بعواطفنا،
generate our emotions.
وتتولد المشاعر.
They lie in the most primitive parts of the brain, linked with energy,
إنهم يقعون في الأجزاء الأكثر بدائية في الدماغ،وترتبط بالطاقة،
focus, craving, motivation, wanting and drive.
التركيز،الشهوة، الحافز الرغبة والدافع.
In this case,
وفي هذه الحالة،
the drive to win life's greatest prize:
الدافع يفوز بأعظم هدايا الحياة:
a mating partner.
شريك الزواج.
They evolved over 4.4 million years ago among our first ancestors,
تطورا منذ أكثر من 4.4 مليون سنة بين أسلافنا الأوائل
and they're not going to change if you swipe left or right on Tinder.
ولن يتغيروا إذا مررت اصبعك يمين أو يسار على tinder.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There's no question that technology is changing the way we court:
ليس هنالك شك بأن التكنولوجيا تُغير الطريقة التي نتودد بها:
emailing, texting,
الرسائل الالكترونية، الرسائل النصية
emojis to express your emotions,
ايموجيز لتعبروا عن مشاعركم
sexting,
رسائل ذات محتوى جنسي
"liking" a photograph, selfies ...
إعجاب بصور،سيلفيز..
We're seeing new rules and taboos for how to court.
نحن نرى قواعد ومحرمات جديدة عن كيفية التودد.
But, you know --
لكن أنتم تعلمون--
is this actually dramatically changing love?
هل هذا يُغير الحب بشكل جذري؟
What about the late 1940s,
ماذا عن أواخر الأربعينيات من القرن الماضي
when the automobile became very popular
عندما أصبح الهاتف الخلوي مشهور جداً
and we suddenly had rolling bedrooms?
وفجأة أصبح لدينا غرف نوم ملفوفة؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How about the introduction of the birth control pill?
ماذا عن بداية حبوب منع الحمل؟
Unchained from the great threat of pregnancy and social ruin,
التحرر من الخطر الكبير من الحمل والدمار الاجتماعي،
women could finally express their primitive and primal sexuality.
أخيراً اصبح بمقدور النساء التعبيرعن حياتهم الجنسية الأولية والبدائية
Even dating sites are not changing love.
حتى مواقع المواعدة لم تُغير الحب.
I'm Chief Scientific Advisor to Match.com,
أنا المستشارالعلمي الرئيسي لموقع match.com
I've been it for 11 years.
كنت في هذا المنصب ل11سنة.
I keep telling them and they agree with me,
كنت باستمرار أقول لهم، وهم يوافقوني الرأي،
that these are not dating sites,
هذه ليست مواقع للمواعدة،
they are introducing sites.
هذه مواقع للتعارف.
When you sit down in a bar,
عندما تجلس في بار،
in a coffee house,
في مقهى،
on a park bench,
على مقعد حديقة،
your ancient brain snaps into action like a sleeping cat awakened,
دماغك القديم يستقر في عمل نوم القط اليقظ،
and you smile
وتبتسم،
and laugh
وتضحك
and listen
وتسمع
and parade the way our ancestors did 100,000 years ago.
وتستعرض كما فعل أسلافنا قبل 100,000 سنة.
We can give you various people --
بإمكاننا أن نعطيك العديد من الناس--
all the dating sites can --
كل مواقع المواعدة تفعل ذات الشيء
but the only real algorithm is your own human brain.
لكن الخوارزمية الحقيقية هي عقلك البشري.
Technology is not going to change that.
التكنولوجيا لن يكون بمقدورها أن تغير هذا.
Technology is also not going to change who you choose to love.
التكنولوجيا أيضاً لن تغير من تختار لتُحب.
I study the biology of personality,
أدرس بيولوجيا الشخصية،
and I've come to believe
ولقد وصلت إلى الاعتقاد
that we've evolved four very broad styles of thinking and behaving,
بأننا طورنا أربع أنماط واسعة من التفكير والتصرف،
linked with the dopamine, serotonin,
وترتبط مع أنظمة الدوبامين، السيروتونين
testosterone and estrogen systems.
هرمون التستوستيرون وهرمون الاستروجين.
So I created a questionnaire directly from brain science
لهذا قمت بصنع استبيان مباشرةً من علم الدماغ
to measure the degree to which you express the traits --
لقياس لأي مدى تُعبر عن الصفات--
the constellation of traits --
كوكبة الصفات--
linked with each of these four brain systems.
المرتبطة بهذه الأنظمة الأربعة.
I then put that questionnaire on various dating sites
من ثم وضعت الاستبيان على العديد من مواقع المواعدة
in 40 countries.
في 40 بلد.
Fourteen million or more people have now taken the questionnaire,
14 مليون شخص أو أكثر جاوبوا على الاستبيان،
and I've been able to watch who's naturally drawn to whom.
وكنت قادرة على مشاهدة بشكل طبيعي من ينجذب إلى من.
And as it turns out,
وكما تبين،
those who were very expressive of the dopamine system
أولئك الذين كانوا معبرين جداً في نظام الدوبامين
tend to be curious, creative, spontaneous, energetic --
يميلون ليكونوا فضولين ، مبدعين،عفويين وحيويين--
I would imagine there's an awful lot of people like that in this room --
بإمكاني أن أتخيل ، يوجد عدد كبير من هؤلاء الأشخاص هنا--
they're drawn to people like themselves.
إنهم ينجذبون لأشخاص يشبهونهم.
Curious, creative people need people like themselves.
الأشخاص الفضولين والمبدعين يريدون أشخاص مثلهم.
People who are very expressive of the serotonin system
الأشخاص الذين عبروا بشكل كبير في نظام السيروتونين
tend to be traditional, conventional, they follow the rules,
يميلون ليكونوا عاديين، تقليديين ويتبعون القواعد،
they respect authority,
يحترمون السلطة،
they tend to be religious -- religiosity is in the serotonin system --
يكونوا متدينين -- التديين هو في النظام السيروتونين--
and traditional people go for traditional people.
والأشخاص العاديين يذهبون للأشخاص العاديين.
In that way, similarity attracts.
بهذا الشكل، التشابه الذي يجذب.
In the other two cases, opposites attract.
في الحالتين الاُخريين، التضداد الذي يجذب.
People very expressive of the testosterone system
الأشخاص الذين يعبرون في النظام التستوستيرون
tend to be analytical, logical, direct, decisive,
يميلوا ليكونوا تحليليين، عقلانيين، واضحين ومحددين
and they go for their opposite:
ويذهبون إلى نقضائهم:
they go for somebody who's high estrogen,
يذهبون لشخص لديه الاستروجين عالي
somebody who's got very good verbal skills
شخص لديه قدرة كلامية ممتازة
and people skills,
ومهارات اجتماعية،
who's very intuitive
ومبادر جداً
and who's very nurturing and emotionally expressive.
شخص مراعي جداً وذو تعبير عاطفي.
We have natural patterns of mate choice.
لدينا أنماط طبيعية لاختيار الشريك.
Modern technology is not going to change who we choose to love.
التكنولوجيا الحديثة لن تغير من نختار لنحب.
But technology is producing one modern trend
ولكن التكنولوجيا تُنتج صيحة جديدة
that I find particularly important.
التي أجدها مهمة بشكل خاص.
It's associated with the concept of paradox of choice.
إنها مرتبطة بمفهوم تناقض الاختيار.
For millions of years,
لملايين السنين،
we lived in little hunting and gathering groups.
عشنا في مجموعات صغيرة للصيد والجمع.
You didn't have the opportunity to choose
لم يكن لدينا فرصة لنختار
between 1,000 people on a dating site.
بين ألف شخص على مواقع المواعدة.
In fact, I've been studying this recently,
في الواقع لقد كنت أدرس هذا حديثاً
and I actually think there's some sort of sweet spot in the brain;
في الحقيقة أنا اعتقد بأن هناك بقعة جميلة في الدماغ؛
I don't know what it is, but apparently, from reading a lot of the data,
لا أعرف ماهي ولكن من الواضح خلال قراءة الكثير من البيانات
we can embrace about five to nine alternatives, and after that,
إنه بإمكاننا قبول من 5 إلى 9 بدائل، ولكن بعد ذلك
you get into what academics call "cognitive overload,"
تحصل على مانسميه أكاديمياً "الزائد المعرفي"
and you don't choose any.
ولا تختار أحد.
So I've come to think that due to this cognitive overload,
لهذا إذا بناءاً على هذا الحمل المعرفي الزائد
we're ushering in a new form of courtship
نستهل نوع جديد من التودد
that I call "slow love."
نسميه "حب بطيء"
I arrived at this during my work with Match.com.
وصلت لهذه النتيجة خلال عملي مع match.com
Every year for the last six years,
كل سنة من السنوات الست الماضية
we've done a study called "Singles in America."
عملنا على دراسة تُدعى "العازبون في أمريكا"
We don't poll the Match population,
نحن لم نرفع تعداد موقع match
we poll the American population.
رفعنا تعداد السكان الأمريكيين.
We use 5,000-plus people,
استخدمنا 5000 شخص واكثر
a representative sample of Americans based on the US census.
عينية تمثيلية من تعداد الشعب الأمريكي.
We've got data now on over 30,000 people,
لدينا أكثر من 30 ألف بيانات شخصية
and every single year,
وفي كل عام،
I see some of the same patterns.
أرى بعض النماذج المتشابهة.
Every single year when I ask the question,
كل عام ،حين أسأل سؤال
over 50 percent of people have had a one-night stand --
أكثر من 50 % من الأشخاص حصلوا على علاقة عابرة--
not necessarily last year, but in their lives --
ليس ضرورياً في السنة الماضية ولكن في حياتهم بشكل عام--
50 percent have had a friends with benefits
50% لديهم أصدقاء منفعة
during the course of their lives,
خلال مسيرة حياتهم،
and over 50 percent have lived with a person long-term
وأكثرمن 50% عاشوا فترة طويلة مع شخص
before marrying.
قبل الزواج.
Americans think that this is reckless.
يعتقد الأمريكيون بأن هذا متهور.
I have doubted that for a long time;
لقد شككت بهذا الأمر لمدة طويلة؛
the patterns are too strong.
الأنماط قوية جداً.
There's got to be some Darwinian explanation --
يجب أن يكون هناك تفسير دارويني--
Not that many people are crazy.
ليس الكثير من الناس مجانين.
And I stumbled, then, on a statistic that really came home to me.
وتعثرت بإحصائية ، عادت بي للبداية.
It was a very interesting academic article
كانت مقالة أكاديمية مثيرة
in which I found that 67 percent of singles in America today
وجدت فيها بأن 67 بالمئة من العازبين في أمريكا اليوم
who are living long-term with somebody,
يعيشون في علاقة طويلة مع شخص ما،
have not yet married because they are terrified of divorce.
ولم يتزوجوا بعد لأنهم خائفون من الطلاق.
They're terrified of the social,
هم خائفون من العواقب -الاجتماعية
legal, emotional,
القانونية ، العاطفية،
economic consequences of divorce.
الإقتصادية ، -للزواج.
So I came to realize that I don't think this is recklessness;
لهذا لا أعتقد بأن هذا تهور؛
I think it's caution.
أعتقد بأنه حذر.
Today's singles want to know every single thing about a partner
عازبون اليوم يريدون أن يعرفوا كل شيء عن الشريك
before they wed.
قبل أن يتزوجوا.
You learn a lot between the sheets,
تتعلم الكثير بين الشراشف،
not only about how somebody makes love,
ليس فقط كيف يمارس هذا الشخص الحب،
but whether they're kind,
ولكن إذا ما كان لطيف،
whether they can listen
إذا ما كان يُصغي
and at my age,
وفي عمري،
whether they've got a sense of humor.
إذا ماكان لديه حس الفكاهة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in an age where we have too many choices,
وفي عمر ، حيث لدينا اختيارات كثيرة،
we have very little fear of pregnancy and disease
ليس لدينا قلق كبير من الحمل والأمراض
and we've got no feeling of shame for sex before marriage,
وليس لدينا شعور بالعار من الجنس قبل الزواج،
I think people are taking their time to love.
أعتقد بأن الناس يأخذون وقتهم بالحب.
And actually, what's happening is,
وفي الحقيقة ، مايحدث هو
what we're seeing is a real expansion of the precommitment stage
مانراه الآن التوسع الحقيقي لمرحلة ماقبل الالتزام
before you tie the knot.
قبل أن تتزوج.
Where marriage used to be the beginning of a relationship,
حيث كان الزواج في بداية العلاقة،
now it's the finale.
الان في النهاية.
But the human brain --
لكن دماغ الإنسان--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The human brain always triumphs,
دماغ الإنسان دائما ينتصر ،
and indeed, in the United States today,
وبالتأكيد الولايات المتحدة اليوم
86 percent of Americans will marry by age 49.
86% من الأمريكان سيتزوجون بعمر 49.
And even in cultures around the world where they're not marrying as often,
وحتى في الحضارات عبر العالم حيث لا يوجد زواج غالباً
they are settling down eventually with a long-term partner.
إنهم يستقرون في نهاية المطاف مع شريك في علاقة طويلة.
So it began to occur to me:
لهذا بدء يتراءى لي :
during this long extension of the precommitment stage,
خلال هذا التوسع في مرحلة ماقبل الالتزام،
if you can get rid of bad relationships before you marry,
إذا كان بإمكانك التخلص من العلاقات السيئة قبل أن تتزوج.
maybe we're going to see more happy marriages.
ربما لكنا رأينا زيجات سعيدة أكثر.
So I did a study of 1,100 married people in America --
لهذا قمت بدراسة ل1.100 شخص متزوج في أمريكا--
not on Match.com, of course --
ليس على موقع match.com ، بالطبع
and I asked them a lot of questions.
وسألت الكثير من الأسئلة
But one of the questions was,
ولكن كان سؤال من الأسئلة،
"Would you re-marry the person you're currently married to?"
"هل ستتزوج مرة أخرى الشخص ذاته"
And 81 percent said, "Yes."
81% قالوا "نعم"
In fact, the greatest change in modern romance and family life
في الواقع ، أكبر تغيير في الرومانسية العصرية والحياة الأسرية
is not technology.
هو ليس التكنولوجيا.
It's not even slow love.
ولا حتى الحب البطيء
It's actually women piling into the job market
إن هذا ليس حب بطيء حتى , بل النساء تتراكم في سوق العمل
in cultures around the world.
في الحضارات عبر العالم.
For millions of years,
لملايين السنين
our ancestors lived in little hunting and gathering groups.
أسلافنا عاشوا في جماعات صغيرة للصيد والجمع.
Women commuted to work to gather their fruits and vegetables.
النساء التزموا بعمل جمع الفواكه والخضراوات.
They came home with 60 to 80 percent of the evening meal.
يرجعون للمنزل مع 60 إلى 80 بالمئة من وجبة العشاء.
The double-income family was the rule.
القاعدة في العائلة كانت الدخل المزدوج.
And women were regarded as just as economically, socially
والنساء يُعاملون ككفوء للرجل اقتصاديا،اجتماعيا
and sexually powerful as men.
وفي القوة الجنسية.
Then the environment changed some 10,000 years ago,
من حوالي 10 الاف سنة ماضية البيئة تغيرت
we began to settle down on the farm
بدأنا بالاستقرار في المزارع
and both men and women became obliged, really,
وكل من الرجال والنساء أصبحوا ملتزمين جدياً
to marry the right person,
بأن يتزوجو الشخص الصحيح،
from the right background,
من الخلفية الصحيحة،
from the right religion
من الدين المناسب
and from the right kin and social and political connections.
من القرابة المناسبة والصلات الاجتماعية والسياسية.
Men's jobs became more important:
عمل الرجال أصبح أكثر أهمية:
they had to move the rocks, fell the trees, plow the land.
يجب عليهم أن يحركو الأحجار، يقطفوا الأشجار، ويحرثوا الأرض.
They brought the produce to local markets, and came home
يحضروا المحصول إلى السوق المحلية ويعودوا إلى المنزل
with the equivalent of money.
مع مايعادل من المال.
Along with this,
جنباً إلى جنب ،
we see a rise of a host of beliefs:
مع ارتفاع مجموعة من المعتقدات:
the belief of virginity at marriage,
معتقد العذرية قبل الزواج،
arranged marriages -- strictly arranged marriages --
الزيجات المدبرة-- الزيجات المدبرة بصرامة--
the belief that the man is the head of the household,
معتقد بأن الرجل هو القائم بالمنزل
that the wife's place is in the home
وبأن مكان الزوجة هو بيتها
and most important,
والأهم
honor thy husband, and 'til death do us part.
أن تكرم الزوج إلى أن يفرقهم الموت.
These are gone.
كل هذه الأشياء ذهبت.
They are going, and in many places,
لقد ذهبت، كذلك الأمر في أماكن عديدة
they are gone.
لقد وّلت.
We are right now in a marriage revolution.
نحن الآن في ثورة الزواج.
We are shedding 10,000 years of our farming tradition
فذلك كان 10 الاف سنة من تقاليدنا الزراعية
and moving forward towards egalitarian relationships between the sexes --
نحن الآن نمضي قدماً في المساواة في العلاقات بين الجنسين
something I regard as highly compatible with the ancient human spirit.
وهذا شيء اعتبره متوافق للغاية مع روح الانسان القديم
I'm not a Pollyanna;
أنا لست بولونية؛
there's a great deal to cry about.
هنالك الكثير يمكن البكاء عليه.
I've studied divorce in 80 cultures,
لقد درست الطلاق في 80 حضارة،
I've studied, as I say, adultery in many --
وكما قلت سابقا لقد درست الزنا في العديد--
there's a whole pile of problems.
هناك تراكم للمشاكل.
As William Butler Yeats, the poet, once said,
وكما قال مرة، الشاعر ويليام بتلر ييتس،
"Love is the crooked thing."
"الحب شيء ملتوي"
I would add, "Nobody gets out alive."
وأضيف "لا أحد يخرج منه حياً"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We all have problems.
جميعنا لدينا مشاكل.
But in fact, I think the poet Randall Jarrell really sums it up best.
ولكن في الواقع ، الشاعر راندل جاريل ، يُلخص الموضوع بنحو أفضل.
He said, "The dark, uneasy world of family life --
يقول:"الظلام ، والعالم الغير مستقر في الحياة الأسرية--
where the greatest can fail, and the humblest succeed."
حيث العظيم يمكن أن يخسر والمتواضع ينجح."
But I will leave you with this:
ولكن سأترككم مع هذا:
love and attachment will prevail,
الحب والتعلق سيسود،
technology cannot change it.
التكنولوجيا لا يمكنها تغيير هذا.
And I will conclude by saying
وسأختم بقول
any understanding of human relationships must take into account
أي فهم في العلاقات البشرية يجب أن يُؤخذ بالحسبان
one the most powerful determinants of human behavior:
أحد المحددات القوية للسلوك البشري:
the unquenchable,
التي لاترتوي،
adaptable
والقادرة على التكيف
and primordial human drive to love.
والدافع الأساسي للإنسان، الحب.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Kelly Stoetzel: Thank you so much for that, Helen.
(كيلي ستوتزيل) شكراً جزيلاً لكِ ، هيلين.
As you know, there's another speaker here with us
كما تعرفون هنالك متحدث آخر معنا اليوم
that works in your same field.
تعمل في نفس مجالك.
She comes at it from a different perspective.
تناولت الموضوع من منظور مختلف.
Esther Perel is a psychotherapist who works with couples.
ايستر بيريل هي معالجة نفسية تعمل مع الأزواج.
You study data,
أنتي تدرسين البيانات،
Esther studies the stories the couples tell her
ايستر تدرس القصص التي يخبرها الأزواج
when they come to her for help.
عندما يأتون طلباً لمساعدتها.
Let's have her join us on the stage.
دعونا نستقبلها هنا على المسرح.
Esther?
ايستر؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So Esther,
ايستر ،إذاً
when you were watching Helen's talk,
عندما كنتِ تُشاهدين حديث هيلين
was there any part of it
هل كان هناك جزءاً منه
that resonated with you through the lens of your own work
تردد معك عبر منظور عملك
that you'd like to comment on?
تريدين التعليق عليه؟
Esther Perel: It's interesting, because on the one hand,
(ايستر بيريل) هذا ممتع ، لأنه من جهة
the need for love is ubiquitous and universal.
الحاجة إلى الحب هي في كل مكان وعالمية.
But the way we love --
ولكن الطريقة التي نحب فيها--
the meaning we make out of it --
المعنى الذي نستخرجه منه--
the rules that govern our relationships, I think,
القواعد التي تحكم علاقاتنا، أعتقد،
are changing fundamentally.
بأنها تتغير جذرياُ.
We come from a model that, until now,
نأتي من النموذج ، الذي حتى الآن
was primarily regulated around duty and obligation,
يخضع حول الواجب والالتزام،
the needs of the collective and loyalty.
والاحتياجات الجماعية والولاء.
And we have shifted it
وقد بدلنا هذا النموذج
to a model of free choice and individual rights,
لنموذج الاختيار الحر وحقوق الفرد،
and self-fulfillment and happiness.
والشعور بالرضا والسعادة.
And so, that was the first thing I thought,
ولهذا إذاً كان أول شيء أفكر به
that the need doesn't change,
بأن الحاجة لا تتغير،
but the context and the way we regulate these relationships
ولكن المضمون والطريقة التي نُخضِع بها علاقاتنا
changes a lot.
تتغير بكثرة.
On the paradox of choice --
في مفارقة الاختيار--
you know, on the one hand we relish the novelty
أنتم تعلمون، من جهة نحن نستمتع بالجدية
and the playfulness, I think,
والهرج ، أعتقد ،
to be able to have so many options.
لنستطيع أن نحظى بكثير من الخيارات.
And at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت،
as you talk about this cognitive overload,
الذي تتكلمون فيه عن الحمل المعرفي الزائد،
I see many, many people who ...
أرى الكثير والكثير من الناس الذين...
who dread the uncertainty and self-doubt
تتملكهم الرهبة والشك والشك الذاتي
that comes with this massa of choice,
الذي يأتي من كثرة هذه الخيارات،
creating a case of "FOMO"
ويخلق حالة من "فومو"
and then leading us --
ومن ثم يقودنا--
FOMO, fear of missed opportunity, or fear of missing out --
fomo اختصار لـ الخوف من إضاعة الفرص أو الخوف من الإخطاء
it's like, "How do I know I have found 'the one' --
إنه شبيه لـ"كيف لي أن أعرف بأني وجدت الذي أريد-
the right one?"
الشخص الصحيح؟"
So we've created what I call this thing of "stable ambiguity."
إذاً نكون قد خلقنا مايسمى "الغموض الثابت."
Stable ambiguity is when you are too afraid to be alone
الغموض الثابت هو عندما تكون خائف جداً من الوحدة
but also not really willing to engage in intimacy-building.
ولكن أيضاً لست على استعداد من البدء في علاقة حميمة.
It's a set of tactics that kind of prolong the uncertainty of a relationship
إنها مجموعة من التكتيكات التي تُطيل أمد الشك بإقامة علاقة
but also the uncertainty of the breakup.
ولكن أيضاً الحيرة في الانفصال.
So, here on the internet you have three major ones.
إذاً هنا على الانترنت لديكم ثلاث طُرق رئيسية.
One is icing and simmering,
الأولى هي التثليج والتأجيج،
which are great stalling tactics
والتي هي تكتيكات مماطلة كبيرة
that offer a kind of holding pattern
تقدم نوع من الحجز
that emphasizes the undefined nature of a relationship
الذي يُفسر طبيعة العلاقة الغير مُعرّفة
but at the same time gives you enough of a comforting consistency
ولكن في نفس الوقت يعطيك تماسك مريح وكافي
and enough freedom of the undefined boundaries.
وحرية متوفرة للحدود الغير مُرّسمّة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah?
صحيح؟
And then comes ghosting.
ومن ثم تأتي طريقة الشبح.
And ghosting is, basically,
وأن تكون شبح هو بشكل رئيسي
you disappear from this massa of texts on the spot,
أن تختفي من هذه الرسائل الكثيرة على الفور،
and you don't have to deal with the pain that you inflict on another,
ولن يكون هنالك داعي للتعامل مع الألم الذي سببته للآخر،
because you're making it invisible even to yourself.
لأنك تجعله خفياً حتى بالنسبة لك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah?
صحيح؟
So I was thinking -- these words came up for me as I was listening to you,
لهذا كنت أفكر-- هذه الكلمات استوحيتها عندما كنت استمع إليكِ
like how a vocabulary also creates a reality,
كيف للمفردات أن تخلق واقع
and at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت،
that's my question to you:
وهنا سؤالي لكِ:
Do you think when the context changes,
هل تعتقدين بأن المضمون تغير،
it still means that the nature of love remains the same?
إنه مازال يعني بأن طبيعة الحب مازالت كماهي؟
You study the brain and I study people's relationships and stories,
أنتِ تدرسين الدماغ وأنا أدرس علاقات الناس وقصصهم،
so I think it's everything you say, plus.
لهذا أعتقد بأن كل ماتقولينه زائد.
But I don't always know the degree to which a changing context ...
ولكن لا أعرف دائما لأي درجة يتغير المضمون...
Does it at some point begin to change --
هل يبدأ بالتغير في درجة معينة
If the meaning changes, does it change the need,
إذا تغير المعنى هل تتغير الحاجة ،
or is the need clear of the entire context?
أو هل الحاجة واضحة للمضمون الكلي؟
HF: Wow! Well --
واو!--حسناً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well, I've got three points here, right?
حسناً ، حصلت على ثلاث نقاط هنا صحيح؟
First of all, to your first one:
أولاً، بالنسبة لسؤالك الأول:
there's no question that we've changed, that we now want a person to love,
ليس هنالك مجال للتساؤل بأننا تغيرنا ،وبأننا الآن بحاجة شخص لنحب
and for thousands of years, we had to marry the right person
ومنذ آلاف السنين ، يجب علينا أن نتزوج الشخص الصحيح
from the right background and right kin connection.
من الخلفية الصحيحة والاتصال الصحيح.
And in fact, in my studies of 5,000 people every year,
في الواقع ، بدراساتي ل5 الاف شخص كل عام
I ask them, "What are you looking for?"
أسالهم "ما الذي تبحث عنه؟"
And every single year, over 97 percent say --
وفي كل سنة أكثر من 97 بالمئة يقولون--
EP: The list grows --
تزايدت القائمة--
HF: Well, no.
حسناً،لا.
The basic thing is over 97 percent of people
الشيء الأساسي هو أكثر من 97% من الناس
want somebody that respects them,
يريدون شخص يحترمهم،
somebody they can trust and confide in,
شخص بإمكانهم أن يثقوا ويثق بهم
somebody who makes them laugh,
شخص يجعلهم يضحكون،
somebody who makes enough time for them
شخص يعطيهم الوقت والاهتمام الكافين
and somebody who they find physically attractive.
شخص يجدونه جذاب ظاهرياً.
That never changes.
لا يتغير.
And there's certainly -- you know, there's two parts --
وهناك بالتأكيد --أنتم تعلمون، هناك قسمين--
EP: But you know how I call that?
ولكن أتعلمين ماذا أدعو ذلك؟
That's not what people used to say --
ليس هذا ما اعتاد الناس أن يقولوه--
HF: That's exactly right.
بالضبط هذا صحيح.
EP: They said they wanted somebody with whom they have companionship,
هم يقولون ، نريد شخص نستمتع برفقته،
economic support, children.
يدعم اقتصادياً، أطفال.
We went from a production economy to a service economy.
اتجهنا من الانتاج الاقتصادي إلى الانتاج الخدمي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We did it in the larger culture, and we're doing it in marriage.
لقد فعلناها بثقافة أكبر ونفعلها في الزواج.
HF: Right, no question about it.
صحيح، هذا بلا شك.
But it's interesting, the millennials actually want to be very good parents,
ولكن إنه من الممتع،بأن جيل الألفية يريدون أن يصبحوا أهل جيدين
whereas the generation above them wants to have a very fine marriage
في حين الجيل الذي سبقهم يريدون الحصول على زواج رائع
but is not as focused on being a good parent.
ولكن ليس بالتركيز نفسه على موضوع الأهل الجيدين.
You see all of these nuances.
ترون كل هذه الفروق.
There's two basic parts of personality:
هنالك قسمين رئيسين للشخصية:
there's your culture -- everything you grew up to do and believe and say --
هناك ثقافتك--كل شيء تربيت عليه وآمنت به وقلته--
and there's your temperament.
وهناك مزاجك الخاص.
Basically, what I've been talking about is your temperament.
أساساً، ماكنت أتحدث عنه هو مزاجك الخاص.
And that temperament is certainly going to change with changing times
وهذا المزاج بالتأكيد سيتغير بتغيير الأزمنة
and changing beliefs.
وبتغيير المعتقدات .
And in terms of the paradox of choice,
ومن حيث التناقض في الاختيار،
there's no question about it that this is a pickle.
ليس هناك شك في ذلك هذا مأزق.
There were millions of years where you found that sweet boy
منذ ملايين السنين ،حيث وجدتي ذلك الشاب الجميل
at the other side of the water hole,
في الطرف الآخر
and you went for it.
وذهبتي للحصول عليه.
EP: Yes, but you --
نعم،ولكن أنت--
HF: I do want to say one more thing.
أريد أن أقول شيء آخر .
The bottom line is, in hunting and gathering societies,
خلاصة القول، في المطاردة وجمع المجتمعات،
they tended to have two or three partners during the course of their lives.
اعتادو الحصول على اثنان أو ثلاث أزواج على مدى حياتهم
They weren't square!
لم يكون أربعة!
And I'm not suggesting that we do,
ولست أقترح بأننا نفعل ذلك,
but the bottom line is, we've always had alternatives.
ولكن في النهاية لدينا دائماً احتمالات بديلة.
Mankind is always --
البشر دائماً--
in fact, the brain is well-built to what we call "equilibrate,"
في الحقيقة ، الدماغ مبني بشكل جيد على مانسميه "التوازن"
to try and decide:
للمحاولة واتخاذ القرار:
Do I come, do I stay? Do I go, do I stay?
هل آتي؟،هل أبقى؟هل أذهب، هل أبقى؟
What are the opportunities here?
ماهي الاحتمالات هنا؟
How do I handle this there?
كيف يمكنني أن اتعامل مع هذا
And so I think we're seeing another play-out of that now.
ولهذا اعتقد بأننا نشاهد الخروج من هذا الان
KS: Well, thank you both so much.
حسناً، شكراً جزيلاً لكما .
I think you're going to have a million dinner partners for tonight!
اعتقد ستحظون بمليون شريك على العشاء اليوم
(Applause)
تصفيق
Thank you, thank you.
شكراً لكم، شكراً.